<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Things plain and weighty referred unto the consideration of both Houses of Parliament assembled at Westminster, March 25, 1690 that peace and happiness, truth and justice, religion and piety, may be established amongst us throughout all generations.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61229</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10445609</idno>
  <idno type="VID">45047</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240882999</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10445609</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1390:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Things plain and weighty referred unto the consideration of both Houses of Parliament assembled at Westminster, March 25, 1690 that peace and happiness, truth and justice, religion and piety, may be established amongst us throughout all generations.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>And now reprinted with the addition of more words of truth ...</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Richard Stafford.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45047:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45047:1"/>
            <p>THINGS Plain and Weighty, REFERRED Unto the Consideration of both Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Assembled at <hi>Westminster, March</hi> 25. 1690. <hi>That Peace and Happiness, Truth and Justice, Religion and Piety, may be Established amongst us throughout all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Reprinted with the Addition of more <hi>WORDS OF TRƲTH,</hi> to prove whether as yet, at what Time, or Place soever Assembled, <hi>They will hearken unto, and Obey the Law of their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>For the Transgression of a Land, many are the Princes thereof: but by a Man of Understanding and Knowledge, the state thereof shall be prolonged,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 28 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Therefore my People are gon into Captivity, because they have no Knowledge; and their Honourable Men are Famished, and their Multitude are dried up with Thirst,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Isa. 5.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The People of the Land have used Oppression and exercised Robbery, and have vexed the Poor and Needy; yea, they have Oppressed the Stranger wrongfully: And I sought for a Man among them, that should make up the Hedge, and stand in the Gap before me for the Land, that I should not destroy it; but I found none. Therefore have I poured out my Indignation upon them, I have consumed them with the Fire of my Wrath: their own way have I recompenced upon their Heads, saith the Lord God,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek. 22.29, 30, 31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the First Month, in the Year 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45047:2"/>
            <p>it; as if <hi>Thou wort altogether such a one as themselves.</hi> I am astonished to think of this horrible Perverting of thy Ways and Nature: Men would not presume to sin thus <hi>With a high hand,</hi> nor yet dishonour God after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but now <hi>They are doing these Things, and thou keepest silence,</hi> Psal. 50.21. And though thou seest all the <hi>Evil, Iniquity</hi> and <hi>Treachery,</hi> that is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; yet <hi>Thou holdest thy Tongue when the wicked Man devoureth the Man that is more Righteous than he,</hi> Hab. 1.13. And if God did not now <hi>keep silence,</hi> and <hi>hold his Tongue,</hi> there could be no Tryal whether they would do thus or not. But notwithstanding all the Practices of Hypocrites, and the Wicked, (through which Strangers and the Ignorant may misapprehend the God whom we serve) thou wilt be Justified when thou speakest, and be clear when thou Judgest at the last and great Day: And even now thou art in this, and all other Matters, as thou speakest in thy <hi>WORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the New Testament observed, by his own Example, what he Taught and Commanded to others. When he was betray'd into the Hands of wicked Men, though he could have had more then Twelve Legions of Angels, yet he made not the least Opposition. He was the Son of God, <hi>King of Kings</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> and consequently exempt from paying of Tribute unto them, as himself reasons, <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.25. Yet rather than he would <hi>give Offence,</hi> he wrought a Miracle for the Payment thereof. And has left this standing Commandment to all his Followers, <hi>Render unto Caesar the Things which are Caesars,</hi> Matt. 22.21. Now the principal Thing belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him is <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Ligeance,</hi> as it is more particularly Explained, Rom. 1.13. <hi>Wherefore ye must needs be subject not only for Wrath, but also for Conscience sake. Render to all their Dues; Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Custom to whom Custom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour.</hi> These Things are as much due to the Supreame Magistrate, as is the common Duty of a Child to a Parent. He hath the same Right to them from his Subjects, which they have to their Goods, Estate or Honour. The Doctrine of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Obedience to Governours is laid down in as plain Terms, as any other Duty in the Gospel, and are sufficient to convince him who acts in Sincerity and Truth.</p>
            <p>But those which are <hi>Presumptuous, Self-willed,</hi> of Troubled and Seditious Spirits, have found out some little and trifling Evasions against these express Texts. There is a way in the World of putting Interpretations, when there is no more need of them, than is to the most plain, obvious and common Expression. But this is a Trick either to wrest, or make the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God of none effect. The Wicked thus vindicate, or palliate their Transgression, and others in like manner justifie Rebellion. Let all Men in general remember, and take heed, That the great Law-giver, when every one comes to give account before him, will not be trifled with: Such Ways and Devices will not now pass in humane Courts and Judicatories. These <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil,</hi> these <hi>Enemies of all Righteousness,</hi> have so much the more to answer for; for <hi>They do not cease to pervert the right Ways of the Lord;</hi> making his Word, as it were, a Nose of Wax (some have Blasphemously called it so) to stamp any Impression, and mould it to any Shape, as serves their base sinister Designs, or present Purposes. In the end such Men will find that the <hi>All-wise God</hi> will not be out-witted by them. The Criminals are not to make their own Construction of the Laws against which they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45047:2"/>have Offended, but must receive according to his righteous Judgment; and then <hi>The Wrath of God which is now revealed from Heaven against all unrighteousness of Men, who hold the Truth in unrighteousness,</hi> Rom. 1.18. shall be actually executed upon them. And likewise will be rendred unto them <hi>That are Contentious and do not obey the Truth, but obey Ʋnrighteousness, Indignation and Wrath,</hi> Rom. 2.8. So they will really wish they had obey'd it, but it is then too late, when the time of Tryal is over. This is as certain and true, as that the Scripture will be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Thus some among us (<hi>who seem to be Religious,</hi> but by failure in one Duty it may be pronounced <hi>their Religion is vain,</hi> Jam. 1.26.) do acknowledge Men ought to pay Obedience unto Governours; but then they say, These Commands extend only to those Kings who love Christ, and themselves live Obedient to his Law. And whether they do or not, private Persons are made Judges; and if they think, such an one doth not, Subjects may lawfully disobey and rebel against him. If this should be granted, no King (howsoever Good or Righteous) would be safe in his Person; for so apt are Men in judging the Worst, especially of those above them, that they would censure him to be a prophane Person, or an Hypocrite. If he was another <hi>David,</hi> a Man after God's own Heart, (even he was hated and spoken against) he would not be after their liking. Then they would not have this Man reign over them; they will outwardly conclude him to be an Enemy to <hi>Jesus,</hi> and pronounce it as lawful to destroy him as Bears and Wolves. Whether lie is so or not, an uncharitable Opinion or false Accusation is sufficient Ground with them to kill <hi>The Lords Anointed,</hi> against whom none could ever lift up his Hand and be Guiltless. This hath been the Divinity of some, and Mischievous in its Effects; but let it be examined by that Word, which is to try the Doctrines, whether they be of Men or no.</p>
            <p>Christ delivered that Command, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.21. of Submission to Magistrates at that very time, when <hi>Caesar</hi> an Heathen Emperour was in the Throne, and <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> were Subordinate Governours. When our Saviour was going to suffer Death by unjust Judgment, <hi>Peter</hi> would have fought in defence of his Master, but was commanded to put up his Sword in the Sheaf. His Apostles preached the same Doctrine, as may be seen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Which was after the Kings of the Earth stood up, and the Rulers were gathered together against the Lord and against his Christ.</hi> For these Epistles of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> were written after that which is spoken of in <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 4. All this considered together, doth manifest that many Teachers and Writers have interpreted the Gospel contrary to what the First <hi>Evangelists</hi> and <hi>Apostles</hi> intended; and these of later Times have put that Restriction, which they never designed. O ye Perverters of the meaning of the Holy Ghost, What Authority have ye to do these Things? By your Expositions and Glosses, ye have diminished from the universal Obligation of the Commands. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do ye make distinctions, where the Law maketh none? To go back to the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> wherein ye so much trust, What do ye think of <hi>Saul,</hi> from whom God had rent the Kingdom, and gave it to one better than he? And though <hi>Saul</hi> did seek after his Life, yet during all the Days God had appointed to <hi>Saul, David</hi>'s Faithfulness and Duty to him may be seen in the Books of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet. There were many wicked Kings in <hi>Israel,</hi> yet to none did the People hence take occasion to rebel, or refuse their
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45047:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45047:3"/>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45047:4"/>lawful Injunctions; neither is the least intimation from Gods Word so to do. It was not because they were Jews and so the <hi>Anointed of the Lord,</hi> but even <hi>Cyrus,</hi> a Gentile, is thus called, <hi>Isa.</hi> 45.1. and unto<note n="*" place="margin">Who was driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and after he was some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for his Pride, his Counsellors and his Lords sought unto him, and he was Established in his Kingdom, <hi>Dan. 4.36.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar God gave the Kingdom,</hi> Dan. 2.37. So they are indefinitely called <hi>Gods Ministers,</hi> Rom. 13.6. it is not said of that single one, but of all in general. The Kings rule several Countries, but over them all is the great King of the whole Earth, <hi>The Lord and Governour of the World.</hi> And he having ordained such relational Duties between King and Subjects, Father and Children, Master and Servants, the Reason is alike in all, and <hi>We are to be subject to our Kings with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward; for this is thank Worthy if a Man for Conscience toward God, endure Grief, suffering wrongfully,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou shalt not speak evil of the Ruler of thy People,</hi> Acts 23.5. upon no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, although he who is to <hi>Govern after the Law, should command Things to be done contrary to the Law;</hi> yet still no abusive or undecent Language is to be used concerning him. In the Original place, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. it is doubly forbid to lay on greater enforcement, <hi>Thou shalt not revile the Gods, nor curse the Ruler of thy People.</hi> But throughout this whole Nation of <hi>England,</hi> They have <hi>Cursed their King,</hi> Isa. 8.21. and have spoken all manner of Evil and Falshood against him; <hi>Neither can they prove the Things whereof they have accused him.</hi> How do Men forget, or over-look such plain Commands? when they are quick enough to find out any Thing in his Word, that may be wrested to serve their wrong designs. When they meet with such, They set their Brains on work for a plausible Interpretation to delude the Hearts of the Simple. They neglected to <hi>Put them in mind to be subject to the Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers, to obey Magistrates,</hi> Tit. 3.1. Whereas if they could bring any Thing out of the <hi>Old Testament</hi> of <hi>Zeal for the Lord of Hosts</hi> and <hi>Fighting his Battels,</hi> this was managed with all their Skill and Dexterity to stir up Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Rebellion: But for those against it, They did either omit, or fallen their own Sence, quite turning that of the Holy Spirit. And even in these Days such an Example of one who did a great act of Injustice or Oppression, shall by the <hi>slight of Men</hi> be alledged out of Scripture to make it seem law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and justifiable. And they have learnt from the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> but not from the <hi>Bible,</hi> to judge or rather pronounce of Things according to the Success: For they do call such a Thing an <hi>Especial Providence</hi> and <hi>Immediate Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance sent by God,</hi> though the Means (by which it came to pass) are against his express Word and written Revelation. They search and wrest the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and speak out whatever may seem to cover, or somewhat excuse their <hi>Ʋniversal Error and Corruption;</hi> But those positive Commands, or plain Texts against it, are either expressed in the general only, or they are omitted, or they put an Interpretation of their own to <hi>Make void thy</hi> Law, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.126. and such <hi>A true saying of God,</hi> of no Signification. To apply Mal. 2.7, 8. <hi>The Priests lips should keep Knowledge, and they should seek the Law at his Mouth, for he is the Messenger of the Lord of Hosts. But ye are departed out of the way, ye have caused many to stumble at both Law and Gospel,</hi> by your Preaching contrary thereunto; <hi>Ye have corrupted the Covenant of Levi and ye have been partial in the Law;</hi> Otherwise ye could not turn Religion into
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45047:4"/>Rebellion; nor alledge the <hi>Word of Righteousness</hi> to maintain unjust Actions' For this doth not allow the least Wickedness, so neither that, which is the greatest Sin, that is commonly committed against Man.</p>
            <p>For Rebellion is against the immediate <hi>Ordinance of God;</hi> which (though it may be suffered for a while) he doth commonly punish and defeat in this Life. On would think, Men might have taken Warning, by them that <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed at the gainsaying of Core,</hi> Jude 11. how the Earth opened and swallowed them up, as if not sit to live above Ground, who would have disturbed that Order and Government there. Though this was set forth for an Example, for all that hereafter should act Rebelliously; yet the Spirit of Disobedience hath so worked in the Minds of Men, that they have not refrained from doing the like Things. Every Age since hath produced Instances of those who have not dyed a Death common to Men. It would be endless to number all the Traytors that have been in our Nation; I am unwilling to accuse mine own Country Men, but I am afraid we are a Reproach to our Neighbours, <hi>That this Country is a Rebellious Country, and hurtful unto Kings,</hi> Ezra 4.15. as by our Records and Histories it doth appear. But if we consult them, we find that several of the Actors have came to a Miserable and Untimely End. If the Business of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> was afar off, and long since, these are later and come home. What if in our own Memory some have been destroy'd in a Rebellious War, others dyed like Dogs, and had their Carkases hanged up for a Spectacle. I speak not this to insult over those poor Creatures; but the Judgments of God (in which may be hidden and reserved Mercy) that have been in our Land, are to be recorded. <hi>That the Inhabitants thereof may learn Righteousness,</hi> and know the Things which belong to their Peace. As the Apostle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. mentioneth the Punishment which fell upon the Jews to dehort others from those Things, which were the occasion thereof; so that may be here represented according to Truth, and the exact Severity which fell upon them, that we may not lust after and do unlawful Things, as some of them lusted and did, and fell and became as the Dung of the Earth. All these Things happened for Ensamples and should be written for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of those which come hereafter. <hi>Happy and safe is he, whosoever shall read and understand, and take heed of these Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Any one, who hath but the common knowledge and fear of God, must be moved with Indignation to hear the <hi>Enemies of the Lord blaspheme,</hi> and <hi>the way of Truth evil spoken off;</hi> to which nothing hath given greater Occasion than the Carriage of the pretended <hi>Religious,</hi> especially in two Things, Disloyalty to the State, and Knavery between Man and Man. Then which nothing is more forbidden in Scripture; which, if rightly understood and obeyed, would make the best Men, and the best Subjects in the World. He who lives accordingly, is an Enemy to none; much less to him whom God hath placed over his People.</p>
            <p>But humane Alterations and Constitutions are commonly long before ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished; and there are in the mean while violent <hi>Contentions</hi> and <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings</hi> among the People: Some crying for this, and another for that; and perhaps neither side knows throughly wherefore. Then the Sword is drawn against our own Country Men. <hi>All the Inhabitants of this Land, even the Kings that sit upon</hi> Davids <hi>Throne, and the Priests, and the Prophets, and all the Inhabitants of</hi> England, <hi>have for several Years been filled with Drunkenness.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45047:5"/>And they have been dashed one against another, even the Fathers and the Sons together,</hi> Jer. 13.13, 14. Neighbours and Kins-folks pursuing one another to Death. <hi>For every Battel of the Warriour is with confused Noise, and Garments rolled in Blood.</hi> We may see goodly Personages wallowing in their own Gore, trodden under Foot and no Man to regard them; We may hear the cruel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of Death bellowing forth Woe and Destruction, the Shrieks and Groans of dying Men. <hi>The Horse-men lifteth up both the bright Sword, and the glittering Spear, and there is a multitude of slain, and a great number of Carkases, and there is none end of their Corpses, they stumble upon their Corpses.</hi> A real Landskip of Misery, occasioned by their own <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Folly.</hi> They thought it at first a fine and gainful Thing to be Disturbers of a quiet State, but such is the Event thereof: and a worse Loss is to be feared further on: for <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions exclude Men out of the Kingdom of God,</hi> Gal. 5.20, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turn us, O God of our Salvation, and cause thine Anger towards us to cease.</hi> That People may come again to their Sobriety and Reason, and lay aside all Malice, and all Guile, and Hypocrisies, and evil Speakings, and Revenge, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousness, Oppression, with all private Designs and Interests of their own. <hi>Surely his Salvation is nigh them that fear him: that Glory may dwell in our Land,</hi> Psal. 85.9. And such, <hi>who fear God,</hi> will indeed do according to his Word and Commandment: Notwithstanding all the Practises of that vast number of Hypocrites, and the Blasphemy, or evil Speaking of them, <hi>Which say they are Christians, but are not;</hi> for they do not obey the Laws of God, nor the Gospel of his Son. They are <hi>Worshippers of God,</hi> but they <hi>do not his Will;</hi> and therefore all their Prayers, for the good of this People, are not heard. <hi>Mercy and Truth are met together: Righteousness and Peace have kissed each other,</hi> Psal. 85.10. Let this Nation but once <hi>do Righteousness,</hi> which is the Commandment and Will of the most high God; and we shall have <hi>Peace. For the work of Righteousness shall be Peace, and the effect of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, Quietness and Assurance for ever. And my People shall dwell in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Habitation, and in sure Dwellings, and in quiet resting Places,</hi> Isa. 32 17.18. If Righteousness were universally done from the highest to the lowest, This also would as certainly be as God's Word is True: And we might give God so much Glory as to believe his assured Promises, and trust upon his invisible Protection. We might <hi>believe in God</hi> (and not say so only in the Words of our Creed) that it shall be even so, as it is here told us.</p>
            <p>As Health is the greatest Good to the natural Body, so is Peace to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. It is better to have a constant Health, but when interrupted by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, then a proper Remedy is seasonable to restore: So in this World of Sin and Confusion, it is better to prevent the mischievous Effects at first; but when they come forth they must be Suppressed again; which may <hi>Be closed up and mollified with Ointment instead of the severer Remedies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Those poor Creatures whose Carkases fell in <hi>Ireland</hi> last <hi>Summer,</hi> or shall be yet killed on the Sea or Land (see <hi>Isa.</hi> 14.16.) will come and say unto me in the other World, <hi>This Man would have preserved our Lives;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it had been done if the King and Parliament had heard the <hi>Word of God</hi> by my Mouth and obeyed it, when this <hi>Testimony</hi> was delivered in unto them on <hi>April,</hi> 2. 1690. But now the Blood of Thousands cries out to the Lord for Vengeance upon the Authors thereof. Though it is now hid from their Eyes, and an unseen Enemy doth hinder them from discerning it; then they will fully know and admire the <hi>Pretiousness and Excellency of Divine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45047:5"/>Truth</hi> which would <hi>preserve Life,</hi> Gen. 45.5. the greatest Good that can be done here. God doth <hi>send it before</hi> for this very End and Purpose; and his <hi>Truth</hi> doth always accomplish this blessed effect where it is understood and received: All Glory and Praise will be given unto God for the same. The same God, who is the <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>Preserver,</hi> will be again the <hi>Restorer</hi> of Mankind. Sirs, ye should have took counsel of God, and have been directed by his Word, not to have done that thing, which occasioned all this Harm and Loss.</p>
            <p>But what if our Rights and Liberties should be Invaded, our true Religion Persecuted, and we compelled to a false one. And those in Authority do take too much upon them, as to become Arbitrary, Unjust and Tyrannical?</p>
            <p>This is the Reasoning of <hi>Flesh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> against the Commandment of the Gospel, and in like manner against forgiving of Injuries. We are not to go according to the dictates of <hi>Fleshly Wisdom,</hi> or of natural and present Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation to <hi>Inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> To submit to a light Inconvenience for that, is very consistent with true Prudence. But this is an Argument from an abuse which may happen; and if that were sufficient to condemn, or surcease a Thing, we might do so as to all; for nothing is so excellent in its own Nature but may be corrupted. The best Things through the baseness of humane Nature are most liable to abuse; and it hath been observed that more Rebellions and Disorders happen under a remiss and easy kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, than what is more Arbitrary and Oppressive. And instance whereof may be in our own Kingdom compared with the Nations round about. But to pursue the Thing higher then from the Inconvenience and Event only. There is not one Obligation or Duty to God or Man, but a seeming Mischief may ensue upon it. He hath been pleased to try our Obedience in such kinds of Relation; if we do our Parts, we may expect the Good and Recompence thereof; others are to perform theirs at their own Peril or Encouragement. Subjects ought not to restrain the Exorbitancy of Kings; for saith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Against a King there is no rising up,</hi> Prov. 30.31. <hi>Where the Word of a King is, there is Power, and who may say unto him, What dost thou?</hi> Eccles 8.4. <hi>Against thee, thee only have I sinned,</hi> Psal. 51.4. said <hi>David</hi> in his Confession to God for the Murther of <hi>Ʋriah;</hi> which shews he was accountable to God only for that wicked Action. In the <hi>New Testament</hi> is a positive Command of Christ, <hi>But I say unto you that ye resist not Evil,</hi> Matt. 5.39. which extends to what is done by those who have Dominion over us, and an Injury offered by a private Person. Yet I will not be afraid to speak out: If either should take advantage over Passive Obedience, or the Forgiving Temper, as to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer or affront the more, it is baseness in the mean while: And it will be determined who Acts best, They who go according to the dictates of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Nature, which is Proud and Cruel; or who have it corrected by the <hi>Wisdom from above,</hi> which makes it <hi>pure, peaceable, gentle and easy to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated.</hi> Let them be never so great in their own, or the Worlds Opinion, they are but Men. And there is one above, <hi>Who shall cut off the Spirit of Princes, he is terrible to the Kings of the Earth,</hi> Psal. 76.12. When they rage most, he can put an Hook in their Jaws, and lead them back from their Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. <hi>Because thy rage against me, and thy tumult is come up into mine Ears: Therefore will I put my Hook in thy Nose, and my Bridle in thy Lips, and I will turn thee back by the way by which thou camest,</hi> Isa. 37.29. What an Ignorant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45047:6"/>Foolish, and Proud Expression (for Pride is made up of Ignorance and Folly) is that of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, And who is that God that shall deliver you out of my Hands,</hi> Dan. 3.15. and when for all his Threatning the Three Children would not comply with his Idolatry and false Worship, <hi>Then was Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar full of fury and the form of his Visage was changed,</hi> Vers. 19. but when God doth in the least manner shew and manifest himself, The proudest two Footed Creature is <hi>astonished</hi> and doth submit: As it afterwards appeared by him. And whosoever now hath the Faith of <hi>Moses,</hi> he doth not <hi>Fear the Wrath of the King, for he endures as seeing him that is Invisible,</hi> Heb. 11.17. For what is a Dying Man to the Eternal God? A Worm of Five or Six Foot long, whose presence is little and circumscribed to a small Room, What is this unto the mighty God, who hath Heaven for his Throne and the Earth for his Foot-stool and filleth all Places and all Things with his Presence. If it be the good Pleasure of our God, he can save his People from the Violence of the greatest Tyrants, or turn them into the <hi>Rod of his Anger,</hi> Isa. 10.5. And then we are patiently to suffer, knowing who striketh, and learn by his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be reformed from our Sins: We may send up Prayers and Tears to him, <hi>In whose Hand is the Heart of the King, and he turneth it whithersoever he will.</hi> God can either alter his Thoughts, or suffer him to fall by an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident or Sickness, see 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9 10. or which way it pleaseth his Almighty Wisdom. <hi>I gave thee a King in mine Anger, and took him away in my Wrath,</hi> Hos. 13.11. <hi>Again they are minished and brought low through Oppression, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and Sorrow. He poureth Contempt upon Princes, and causeth them to wander in the Wilderness, where there is no way. Yet setteth he the Poor on high from Affliction,</hi> Psal. 107.39, 40, 41. He can do it without our as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance; for he doth then more Magnify his own Power: Neither are we to <hi>Break any of these least Commandments and teach Men so,</hi> Matt. 5.19. least we be in danger to be shut out of the Kingdom of Heaven, and in the mean while <hi>We suffer as Evil doers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King is bound by Oath to keep Righteousness, and minister true Judgment unto his People; for the Observation or Neglect of which he is to give account unto God at the last Day. But now they ought to bear some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with one another, there being Faults and Infirmities both in King and People. For if we know the Truth, and search to the bottom, we shall find that those Seeds of Evil within, do make all the disturbance in the World; which are provided against by the Grace of him, who is greater than <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> and then all People might dwell safely every Man under his Vine, and under his Fig-tree, from one end of the Earth to the other, all the Days of our Kings and Governours.</p>
            <p>Yea, Those <hi>Seeds of Evil</hi> shall at length (towards the end of Time) be so perfectly Cured and utterly done away, that all Governours and Government of Men shall for ever cease and determine, for there will be no need there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But <hi>God and Christ will reign alone in that Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Christ, the Eternal Word, hath laid down sure and lasting Foundations of Government, <hi>To order it, and to establish it with Judgment, and with Justice from henceforth even for ever; The zeal of the Lord of Hosts will perform this,</hi> Isa. 9 6 7. The Lord hath given such Laws, Rules, and Directions, to the World, that, if they were observed, would produce a perpetual Peace, and firm Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment throughout the whole Earth: But by Disobedience and turning Aside
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45047:6"/>comes in Confusion and every evil Work, as may be seen by what hath been aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And having manifested the Truth, and shewed those relational Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Subjects, I come now to apply it to the People of <hi>England, viz.</hi> In the late Revolution of putting down one King and setting up another, in this they are a <hi>Nation that have not done Righteousness,</hi> but they have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted,</hi> Rom. 13.2. and <hi>Forsook the Ordinance of their God,</hi> Isa. 58.2. They have actually departed from that established and fixed Order of Things he hath set up. So they are in danger to <hi>Dye in their Sins,</hi> John 8.24. <hi>And shall utterly perish in their own Corruptian,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.12. Now is their Danger nearer than when we first warned them, and the Things do make haste where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have so often foretold them. Much more of their Life is spent, and the day of Immortality is at Hand. So that we do come with the greater Earnestness to rescue them from the place of Torment, to pull them (though never so much against their Wills) <hi>Like Brands out the Pire.</hi> If I should quite let them alone, and they would now have it so, yet if they should <hi>Die in their Sins,</hi> than they will wish otherwise; and will desire exceedingly that they had attended unto what is here laid before them. And that knowing the Time, that they do day by day approach nearer, I do now testifie with the greatest Earnestness and Reality, that their several Persons shall appear before the Judgment Seat of God, to give account, and receive for what they have done concerning this Matter. <hi>Seeing they despised the Oath, by breaking the Covenant (when lo, they had given their Hand) and have done all these Things, they shall not escape. Therefore thus saith the Lord God, as I live, surely mine Oath that they have despised, and my Covenant that they have broken, even it will I recompence upon their own Head,</hi> Ezek. 17.18 19. This is full and direct to the present Purpose; for it was spoken as to the <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> who was an Heathen, and as much an Idolater and Estranged from God as a Popish Prince. But the Almighty doth take the more notice, when through his own People his <hi>Name is prophaned or blasphemed amongst the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</hi> He calls it in a peculiar manner, <hi>Mine Oath,</hi> and <hi>my Covenant.</hi> It is yet a greater Aggravation to <hi>Hold the Truth in Ʋnrighteousness:</hi> It is worse to give Occasion for <hi>The way of Truth to be evil spoken off.</hi> And therefore, when those of the pure Reformed Religion had Sworn a solemn Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy to a King, (whom then they knew to be a Papist) his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note n="*" place="margin">Which is contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish'd to Ʋsurpers and Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> Heirs and Successors, in so strict and particular a manner, as Words can well express; when they had Crown'd him and performed Fealty, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably was a like Ceremony which the Prophet here calls, (When lo, he had given his Hand) to <hi>Despise this Oath,</hi> and <hi>break this Covenant,</hi> makes <hi>Protestanism</hi> stink, and be evil spoken off throughout the World; and offends every one who is zealous for his God, and hath a right Sence of his infinite Holiness and Uprightness.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45047:7"/>
            <p> In this Alteration they did <hi>take Counsel,</hi> but not <hi>of the Lord,</hi> Isa. 30.1. They had respect unto what they thought present Conveniency, but did not consult his Word, nor seek unto him for Direction by Prayers and Humiliation: But it was done by their own Counsels and Manner of Vote. There were about an Hundred and fifty Members in the Lower House, and many in the Upper, who remained stedfast to their Oaths and Duty; and did not consent to the Counsel and Deed of them. And then if we deduct from the other Side, all those who gave their Suffrage either out of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Fear, Interest,</hi> or <hi>Revenge,</hi> or Men pleasing, or some other sinful or ungodly Principle, It will truly appear that the Thing was not done <hi>By the Grace of God,</hi> but by Men of corrupt Minds and Passions. And afterwards <hi>They would cover with a Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but not of my Spirit, that they may add Sin to Sin.</hi> Not knowing, that hereby they do <hi>Treasure up to themselves Wrath against the day of Wrath.</hi> The Scribes and Pharisees of our Time have found out several Glosses, Distinctions, Restrictions, and Sentiments of their own Devising, by which they would slubber over Perjury and sanctifie Injustice. And there was never any Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this nature since the World began, but there have been also found out Priests to justifie it, and Judges and Lawyers to make it legal. But it is manifest from, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Isa.</hi> 5.16. and 61.8. <hi>Job.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Psal.</hi> 33.4. and 111.7, 8. and 145.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. afore cited, and sundry other places of his revealed Word, That this Revolution is none of Gods Work or Doing, in which he is well pleased: Only what he suffers, as he doth all the Sin and Wickedness in the World, and so he did the Manners of the Israelites Fourty Years in the <hi>Wilderness. Wherefore will ye plead with me? Ye all have trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed against me, saith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 2.29.</p>
            <p>Then they did abrogate the former Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and impose a new one. <hi>Shall such escape by Iniquity?</hi> And have done all these Things, they shall not escape. <hi>The Lord looketh from Heaven: he beholdeth all the Sons of Men. From the place of his Habitation he looketh upon all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth. He fashioneth their Hearts alike: He considereth all their Works.</hi> He knoweth all those particular Proceedings from the very beginning to this Time; every Thing they have done day by day, all the several Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, all the lying Stories and false Accusations, the close and hidden Acts of Hypocrisie, all the tricks of <hi>Machiavelian Policy,</hi> and the several kinds of Sin and Wickedness. <hi>These Things have you done, and I kept silence; but I will reprove and set them in order before you.</hi> As they were committed from Time to Time, so will he bring every secret Thing into Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore thus saith the Lord God, as I live, surely mine Oath that they have despised, and my Covenant that they have broken, even it will I recompence upon their own Head.</hi> Here the Threatning is confirmed as much as possible, <hi>as I live,</hi> which is as sure as he is God, which again is as certain as there is a World, and any Thing in it, (for some one must have made all these Things that are made, and he is God.) So certainly will he <hi>Recompence it upon your own Head.</hi> If we mistake not in the History of the Bible, This afterwards happened to be true; for when <hi>Zedeziah</hi> contrary to his Oath rebelled (compare <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 52.) <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> came with his Army against <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and took it, and killed the Sons of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and put his own Eyes out, and slew the <hi>Princes of Judah,</hi> and led the People into Captivity. And how know we, but the same God may yet stir up and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45047:7"/>an Army of <hi>Cruel French</hi> and <hi>Irish</hi> to invade our own Nation? Or suffer the Inhabitants of this Land to fall into Discord and Confusion, as in our late Civil Wars and Commotions. He will punish this National Sin of Perjury either in this World, or the World to come. God is highly provoked and dishonoured by every false Oath. The several Persons, who take it, pray that God would help them according to the Truth they speak and intend to perform; but prevaricating that, their Prayer shall turn into their own Bosom, and so they are in Danger to be destitute of his Aid, without which they shall perish.</p>
            <p>As ye have already despised his Oath, so ye may here despise his Word and Truth; but beware least that also come upon you, <hi>Behold ye Despisers, and wonder and perish.</hi> Take heed least ye provoke God yet more, and so fall into a great degree of his Wrath and sore Displeasure. It is an easie matter to slight it all off, and <hi>Put, away his Statutes from you,</hi> Psal. 18.22. but ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly avoid your own particular Deaths, whereby ye <hi>Fall into the Hands of the living God;</hi> and then he will account with all those who behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Contemptuously and Stubbornly against him. Ye may now look upon these as vain and troublesome Imaginations, and not suffer them to enter into your Mind; <hi>Eat, Drink and be Merry,</hi> have recourse to Company, and so forget or harden your selves against what is here offered unto you; but as soon as ever ye are slipt out of the Flesh, ye will be sensible of the Truth, and Significancy of them, do what ye can. <hi>When the two Prophets shall be slain, They that dwell upon the Earth shall make Merry, and shall send Gifts one to another; because these two Prophets tormented them that dwelt on the Earth,</hi> Rev. 11.10. Whereas it would be some Advantage and Help for them, if they could Eat or Drink any Thing which would make themselves Immortal, and so prevent their own coming to Judgment. But now seeing that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree is past upon all Men, <hi>Once to Die, and after that the Judgment,</hi> they had better hearken, and also comply with those, who would have hindred their approaching Ruin and Condemnation; for though they falsly think so, yet we do not <hi>Torment Men,</hi> but only persuade, exhort and testify that Mankind do repent off, and forsake those Sins, which when put in remembrance off, do cause present Vexation, and (unless prevented after the aforesaid manner) do consign them over unto eternal Death and Misery.</p>
            <p>We have sinned with our Fathers, we have committed Iniquity, we have done Wickedly, <hi>and have Rebelled, even by departing from thy Precepts, and from the Judgments.</hi> This Nation hath slain the Lord's Anointed, for which is kept an Anniversary Day of Humiliation and Repentance. His Son was Twelve Years kept out of his Kingdom, for which also is an Anniversary Day of Thanksgiving, with Forms of Prayer and Devotion answerable to it. <hi>His Brother, who hath the same Right, stands now Excluded.</hi> Be not deceived, God is not mocked: Though he now <hi>Holds his Tongue,</hi> and seems to be <hi>Gon afar off;</hi> yet even now he speaks unto us out of his <hi>Word,</hi> and is not far from every one of us. However we must meet with and appear before him, when the Judge shall testifie himself, and give a clear account how we have Tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed against our God by <hi>Transgressing his Laws, changing the Ordinance and breaking the everlasting Covenant,</hi> Isa. 24.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet now there is hope in Israel concerning this Thing,</hi> Ezra. 10.2. We learn hence and from other plaoes of Scripture, That there is no other way to <hi>Escape,</hi> but to repent, and undo what we have done; for that is the nature
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45047:8"/>of true Repentance, that if it were to do again, we would not do it; and also to undo a Fault as much as can be. Accordingly when ye do once again assemble in Parliament, ye may this know, that no Man or Woman whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, nor any Foreign Prince State, or Potentate hath Power or Authority to prorogue or dissolve your Meeting, but only your Rightful King. And it is the express Command of the Great and Almighty God, <hi>Learn to do Well, seek Judgment, RELIEVE THE OP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESSED,</hi> Isa. 1.17. or as it is in the Margent, <hi>Righten</hi> the Oppressed. So that ye may take <hi>Counsel of the Lord, (whom ye are to obey and keep all his ways)</hi> and by Fasting and Prayer, both Publick and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, seek out of the whole Book of his Commandments, and from thence you may find that ye ought to do Righteousness, and send Commissioners to restore your <hi>Aged and Oppressed King JAMES</hi> to the Seat and Throne of his Fathers; and reinstate him after the same Judiciary Manner, as he was Unrighteously Deprived. Things may be yet Peaceably and Prudently Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justed, and Established upon the <hi>Sure Foundation of Righteousness.</hi> A general and comprehensive Act of Oblivion might pass; and (in this <hi>Great Time</hi> which is drawing on, <hi>of the Reconciliation of all Things.</hi>)<note n="*" place="margin">If it was indeed True and Real, that a cannon Bullet came so near to one as to take off part of his Coat and Wais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, and raise up the Skin of his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This seems to have been a Sign given that God would remove the Government off from his Shoulders, and yet not hurt his Person. He would sooner go to Heaven, if He had continued in that Station the Creator of Mankind had placed him; and if He would now willingly and freely Resign up unto him, whose Right it is.</note> It might be so ordered as it was in the Restauration of <hi>David</hi> after the Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and Rebellion of his Son, <hi>That not so much as one Man be put to death,</hi> 2 Sam. 19.22. All former Transactions may be passed by; and Things for the future may be firmly Establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and secured for Christian Liberty against the undue Incroachments of Popery and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitary Government. <hi>For it shall come to pass in that Day, saith the Lord of Hosts, that I will break his Yoke from off thy Neck, and will burst thy Bonds, and STRANGERS shall no more serve themselves of him. But they shall serve the Lord their God, and David their King, whom I will raise up unto them,</hi> Jer. 30.8, 9.</p>
            <p>Our Nature is somewhat aukward and averse to repent: What to undo and recant? To accuse our selves of Fault, Folly and Shame; to be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and have our Esteem lessened among wise Men; and the Nations round about; all this seems hard in our Natural Proud State. <hi>Surely the Princes of Zoan are Fools, the Counsel of the wise Counsellors of Pharoah is become brutish,</hi> Isa. 19.11. was a blunt, but true Expression of an antient <hi>Prophet;</hi> and is at this Day verified in our own Country. It is somewhat irksome to be told hereof. But yet it is not unreasonable to confess what we cannot deny our Imperfection and want of Foresight. It is an act of Prudence to return from an Errour, and of such an one, who is able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern what is really Good and Profitable. It is an advancement to a better State. Was it not more Unreasonable to do those Things at first, than it is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45047:8"/>now to leave them when they are discovered to be False and Unrighteous? Bur chiefly which should have been mentioned in the First place, seeing ye have offended against a great and good God, ye are required, <hi>Only acknowledge thine Iniquity, that thou hast transgressed against the Lord thy God,</hi> Jer. 3.13. by despising his Oath, breaking his Covenant, and forsaking his Ordinance. Either ye must do this now, which through his Goodness and Mercy may avail to his Forgiveness and Reward; or ye will wish hereafter in vain, ye had done it to turn from your selves Guilt and Condemnation. It is better to be liable unto a little and short Shame at present, and to lose somewhat of your Esteem, (if it should be so) than after your Bodies have for some while slept in the Dust, to <hi>Rise up to Shame and everlasting Contempt,</hi> to be a Scorn and Derision before the general Assembly of Angels and Men at the Judgment of the great Day. Trust ye not your eternal Happiness or Misery to the Imaginations and Sayings of Bishops, Priests and Deacons, who according to Form do pray for the true Knowledge and Understanding of Gods Word;<note n="†" place="margin">Strange! that (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Blindness of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Jews, Acts 13.27.</hi>) People should hear the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures read every day, and yet by not comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of them, they are <hi>Fulfil'd in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to their own Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </note> but by their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Living they do not set it forth, nor shew it accordingly. Nor yet to the Judgment and Decision of some <hi>Temporising. Ʋniversities,</hi> or any other <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Divines,</hi> whose Religion is <hi>Principibus Placuisse viris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who have changed the Truth of God into a Lie;</hi> and have Studied to please <hi>The Creature more than the Creator, who is blessed for ever.</hi> Amen. They have so modelled and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>his Truth,</hi> which <hi>endureth to all Generations,</hi> Psal. 100.5. that it might serve the present juncture of Affairs; and that Themselves might <hi>At all Times</hi> (past, present and to come) <hi>walk according to the course of this World.</hi> Nor yet be ye prevailed upon by the Voice of the Multitude of dying Men, or the <hi>Contradiction of Sinners;</hi> but hearken unto what the <hi>Spirit</hi> saith expresly and clearly, <hi>Little Children let no Man deceive you: He that doth Righteousness, is Righteous, even as he is Righteous. In this the Children of God are Manifest, and the Children of the Devil: Whosoever doth not Righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Brother,</hi> 1 John 3.7, 10. <hi>That no Man</hi> (of whatever Rank or Degree) <hi>go beyond and defraud his Brother</hi> (much less a Father) <hi>in any Matter</hi> (which extends to a Kingdom or Inheritance) <hi>because that the Lord is the Avenger of all such;</hi> as <hi>we have also forewarned you and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified,</hi> 1 Thess. 4.6. now so many times that the <hi>Word is Established.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I take you to record this Day, from henceforth and for ever, that I am pure from the Blood of all Men. For I have not shunned to declare unto you all the Counsel of God. Though for this very Thing only, I have endured Persecution, Danger and Loss; and ye say the same Thing of me as was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly of <hi>Paul,</hi> a Messenger of the Lord, that I am a <hi>Pestilent Fellow,</hi> and a <hi>mover of Sedition,</hi> and <hi>it is not fit he should Live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ye do send me again unto Prison, or proceed against me as an Evil doer, This is to <hi>Add Iniquity to your Iniquity,</hi> and <hi>not to come into thy Righteousness.</hi> Which if ye go on to do, your selves will be <hi>Blotted out of the Book of the Living, and not be written with the Righteous,</hi> Psal. 69.27, 28. It is the same Thing, as if ye should say, <hi>We will not do according to the Laws of God, but Punish or Hang this Fellow for setting them before us.</hi> To persecute him, whom Christ sends, is to <hi>Kick against the Pricks;</hi> which the more fiercely ye do, the more ye will Wound your selves. I am a poor decrepit Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and partake of the same Flesh and Blood; but if ye will prosecute that Manifestation of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Truth of God,</hi> which appears forth through
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45047:9"/>me. This is to <hi>Fight against God.</hi> Acts 5.39. and 23.9. and to inflict Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment on the Godhead himself if he were liable to Suffering; but however because we have Sence and Weakness to receive, and this may be suffered to be in your Power, ye are ready to do the same unto his Servant. It is by some esteemed a piece of Pride and Bravery that <hi>They can do Things against the Truth;</hi> and as their Fathers did before them, <hi>Persecute and kill tho Prophets,</hi> who were appointed to make it known. But let such consider, or they shall feel, that all those who of set Purpose go against those Pillars of Truth (whereby God hath determined to judge the World) will find, That they had better run their Heads against a Stone Wall, which may dash out their Brains, but that remains Unshaken. And when the same God, (who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth away the Generations of Mankind, <hi>as with a floud, they are as a slee<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Psal. 90.5.) shall call them to account for their Usage to those <hi>Prophets <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wise Men, and Scribes</hi> (under which last I am comprised) <hi>whom he se<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Matt. 23.34.<note place="margin">See my printed Apology.</note> Such shall know that they had better let them alone. A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> let those of the present Age, albeit they have humane Authority on their side, take heed to themselves, what they intend to do as touching any one, who doth only bear both Testimony against a National Sin and Corruption, to keep up the Government of him, who is <hi>God of Gods,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords the great King of all the Earth;</hi> and also to assert (notwithstanding all Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression) the eternal and immutable Rules of Judgment and Righteousness.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Stafford, <hi>a Scribe, according to the Promise and Sending of Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe People of this Nation are to take Notice, That these Things being Written and Published will have the same Effect <hi>(To convince them of Sin, and of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, and of Judgment, that they may be without Excuse)</hi> all one as if they were spoken out by word of Mouth, and proclaimed with a loud Voice throughout the several publick Places of our Land.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45047:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>